Guide to the William James Mutch Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
William James Mutch Papers
1834-1947
RG 118
Yale University Divinity School Library
1
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, sermons, notes, and biographical material document the career of William James Mutch as a professor and author of religious education material. William James Mutch (1858-1947) was a Yale-trained Congregational clergyman and Professor of Philosophy and Education at Ripon College, Wisconsin from 1907 to 1925. He was the author of Christian religious education materials, including the well known Graded Bible Stories.
Mutch, William James
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1858 Feb 7 Born in Hillsboro, Wisconsin
1882 B.A. and B.L., University of Wisconsin
1885 B.D., Yale Divinity School
1885-1907 Minister, Howard Avenue Congregational Church, New Haven
1886 Married Rose Prevey who became the mother of James, William Warren, and Helen
1894 Ph.D., Yale1894 Attended Oxford University, England
1901-1902 Lecturer, Christian Pedagogy, Yale Divinity School
1907-1925 Professor of Philosophy and Education, Ripon College, Wisconsin
1947Nov 25 Died
Scope and Contents
This record group documents Mutch's work as a prominent author of religious education curricular materials during the first half of this century.
The Correspondence of Series I primarily relates to Mutch's Graded Bible Studies, which were used extensively in the U. S. and translated into Chinese. Writings and Sermons in Series II include copies of his religious education textbooks as well as a sermon delivered at the 35th anniversary of the Howard Avenue Congregational Church in New Haven, and a memoir by Mutch. The Notes and Lectures of Series III include documention of Mutch's work as a professor at Ripon College.
Some printed materials received with the Mutch Papers have been placed in other Yale Divinity Library record groups. The following materials related to the Howard Avenue Congregational Church in New Haven were placed in Record Group No. 48, New England Church Records:
Manual (annotated) - 1887
Programs for "Service of Praise" - 1887, 1888
List of officers and members - 1888
Manual - 1891
Yearbook - 1892
Historical brochure - 1895
Manual (annotated) - 1897
Program for 35th anniversary program - 1900
Church newsletter - 1901
Sunday School lesson outline - n.d.
The following materials were placed in Record Group No. 56, Congregational Church Records:
Constitution and Rules of the Associated Pastors of New Haven Center - 1873
The Creed and Confession of Faith - 1884
Manual of the New Haven Congregational Club - 1889
Articles of Association and By-Laws of the Congregational Union of New Haven - 1892
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1917-1923, n.d.
II. Writings and Sermons, 1879-1941
III. Notes and Lectures, 1906-1937, n.d.
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1834-1947, n.d.
Christian education -- United States -- Curricula; Educators; Mutch, William James
- Correspondence, 1917-1923, n.d.; Series I
  - From Ralph C. Wells (Weihsien, Shantung, China) re. Chinese translation of Graded Bible Stories, 1917 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From/to Frank Knight Sanders (N.Y.) Re. Introduction for Graded Bible Stories, 1922 Aug 23, 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From/to Lucius C. Porter (N.Y.) Re. Introduction for Graded Bible Stories, 1923 Jan 8, 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To E.G. Tewksbury (Shanghai, China) re. Graded Bible Stories, 1923 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From University of Chicago Press re. Article in Journal of Religion, 1923 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From/to Irene Ruetenik (Cleveland) re. Manual for oral religious teaching (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Writings and Sermons, 1879-1941; Series II
  - Poem in University Press, Madison, Wisconsin, Vol. XI, No. 6, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Adaptation in Missionary Method", published in The New World, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Call of the Multitude", sermon delivered at 35th anniversary of Howard Avenue Congregational Church, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christian Teachings, with holograph notes enclosed, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christian Teachings, British edition, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Christian Nurture, Vol. II, No. 1 (WJM editor), 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Self-Activity in Education and Life", published in Yale Divinity Quarterly, Vol. I, No. 3, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chinese translation of Graded Bible Stories: Vol. I (3rd edition), Vol. III (2nd edition), unidentified volume (n.d.), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "What is Christian Education", published in The Journal of Religion, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Vocational Motive", vesper address at Ripon College, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Syllabus of Congregationalism", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Anniversary Hymn", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publicity sheets for writings of WJM, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Junior Bible lessons (I-XXVI Patriarchs), 1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - History of the Bible, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - How to Interest, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History of the Bible (revised edition), 1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Graded Bible Stories, Books 1, 2, 3, 4, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - "Reminiscences of Long Life", 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Notes and lectures, 1906-1937, n.d; Series III
  - "The Method of Nature": course taught by WJM at Ripon College; Typescript lectures--2 volumes; Holograph notes--5 1/2" by 8 1/2" sheets (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - "The Method of Nature" - Holograph notes (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Community Lecture Series: First Congregational Church, Ripon, 1937 Apr 2-May 14 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notes found in Introduction to Philosophy by Friedrich Paulsen, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous holograph notes 3 1/2" by 4 1/2" sheets (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1834-1947, n.d.; Series IV
  - Biographical documentation, 1881-1947, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manual of Forms of the Presbyterian Church with enclosures, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sunday School merit coupons, etc. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - A Catechism and Prayers by Rev. William Malcolm (Aberdeen), 1834 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tracts published by Religious Tract Society, London (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1924, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Rules and Regulations of the New Haven Caledonian Club, 1884, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 10)